so want to talk about the big things
that need to happen we're living in a
time of unprecedented planetary change
unprecedented nothing like this has ever
happened before there are now more than
7 billion people alive on the planet we
are literally altering the chemistry of
the Earth's crust the ocean and the
atmosphere we're changing the form of
the land itself it's very shape there
was a study that came out almost 15
years ago and geophysical research
letters saying that humans are a
geomorphic agent we are shaping the land
the consequences of our management
practices for land cause more of the
earth to move through wind and soil
erosion wind and water erosion of soil
than by natural processes alone so we're
living in this time where we cannot
avoid thinking about what humanity is
doing and we see the consequences of our
actions at every scale we see it in the
personal Andy internal as we have
spiritual and emotional crises with a
epidemics of gun violence domestic
violence depression suicide despondency
impulsivity and distracted pneus and so
on but we also see it at the scale of
our governing systems that the people
who rise to power often do so through
corrupting filters so there's a process
of selecting those who will serve
systems of corruption
as the means to get people into
positions of power so we could talk
about corruption of money and and
politics lobbying that influences
legislation and all of those things but
more fundamentally we're at a time where
our ability to envision the future has
become grim now it doesn't mean the
future is grand that just means our
ability to do so is we're now three
generations into a period of apocalyptic
thinking so with World War two we add
the bomb and so then we had the period
of popular science fiction and horror
and fantasy being about nuclear
holocaust about radioactive monsters and
we had the Cold War and we had these
periods of time where we felt like very
powerful organized groups of human
beings were inherently a threat but then
we had the period of global anarchy
which was the collapse of legitimate
authority and a decentralization such
that the most dangerous actors are not
state-based or government actors in
there not nation-states their their
guerrilla tactics of decentralized
networks organized not by locale but by
worldview and by story that's where we
have things like terrorism or those who
would rig the financial system to
collapse and then set up legislation to
let them benefit from it as we saw a few
years ago on the positive side we see
new forms of struggle and new forms at
social justice and we see outpouring of
sympathy and compassion every time
there's visible hardship when there are
hurricanes and earthquakes
they're natural disasters of various
kinds there are Wars and bombings and
the things like what happened in Paris
recently or what's happening in Syria
living through this time one thing that
we can see is that the world is changing
more quickly image or actual the world
is more complex than we humans are
equipped to handle so we don't naturally
see the world as emerging decentralized
complexity we don't naturally see the
world as being systemically caused we
don't naturally see the world as being
accelerating and we don't naturally see
exponential rates of change and yet that
is what is happening it can be seen
there are ways to see it there are ways
to learn to see it there is now an
abundance of knowledge in a way we have
too much knowledge meaning it's more
than we know how to handle individually
or at the level of our institutions
we're now about 400 years into a period
of analytic reductionism which means
that we take real world holistic things
and we break them into artificials
simplistic parts because we can manage
the simplicity of those parts so we
divide the world into chemistry and
physics and biology psychology
anthropology sociology we divide the
world into categories so that we can
make sense of it but in putting the
pieces together again we find that we
have the problem of Humpty Dumpty we
can't easily put the pieces back
together again into our institutions
having evolved mostly in the context of
this four-year 400-year trajectory of
analytic reductionism just the right of
the rise of modernity the rise of
Science and Technology
as understood in the scientific age it's
largely a Western phenomenon although
it's been exported to the world and now
we need synthesis we need holism we need
inclusion we need participation and so
now we need to depend on parts of this
knowledge that are more relevant and
strategic so we need knowledge about
emotional well-being we need knowledge
about interpersonal skills we need
knowledge about how to work well in
teams we need knowledge about how to
critique knowledge we need knowledge
about how to visualize knowledge we need
knowledge about how to tell stories
about knowledge we need knowledge about
how to build and improve institutions we
need knowledge of various kinds that are
tacit how two kinds of knowledge like
how do you become a happy well-balanced
person how do you work well on a team
how do you allocate resources for a
project how do you keep a project on
schedule how do you hold yourself and
others accountable these how to's or
what we need to learn because of the
knowledge the factual knowledge the
information knowledge that kind is
prevalent ubiquitous abundant even
excessive with so much of it we can't
possibly use it all but in my
meanderings across different fields of
knowledge and practice I'm finding that
every problem that anyone has that's
been solved by someone somewhere else
every problem the one problem that
hasn't is applying all of those
solutions to our problems we are not
very good at that and we have to learn
how so that is a task for us in
education design in policymaking and
governance in science and research and
the arts and a creative expressions of
humanity and I hope that we're able to
do this I'm deeply inspired by
the human ability to experience awe and
reverence beauty to feel compassion and
empathy and to be curious to want to
know things and for this reason that I
think we're going to make it not only do
I think we're going to make it but I
think the future is going to be better
than we could possibly imagine but
largely not for the reasons that we're
told but the feel-good stories of
poverty reduction or feel-good stories
about economic well-being in a time of
unprecedented inequality in a time when
more people are starving to death every
day then weren't alive in the entirety
of the human race 100 years ago we're
living in a time of great social
injustice great political corruption in
a great miss placing of priorities what
really matters is not what most of us
are doing most of the time so we need to
change this and as always change starts
within it starts where you are it starts
here it starts now so what are you going
to do to be part of the healing process
of helping humanity find balance with
itself and find harmony with the planet
that we depend upon for our survival and
how do we unleash all of that odd that
reverence that compassion that
enthusiasm in our curiosity to make the
transition that we all increasingly feel
deep in our bones is what we must do and
how do we do it together these are
questions and inquiry that I'm exploring
to all of my life in my actions in my
work and I invite you to walk on this
journey with me let's do this